Crossing Borders, Bridging Generations Mixed Heritage Oral History Project 2011.019
Brooklyn Historical Society
Crossing Borders, Bridging Generations Mixed Heritage Oral History Collection
2011-[ongoing]
2011.019
Brooklyn Historical Society
38.0 items
This collection is a part of Crossing Borders, Bridging Generations (CBBG), an oral history project and public programming series, examines the history and experiences of mixed-heritage people and families, cultural hybridity, race, ethnicity, and identity in the historically diverse borough of Brooklyn. The oral history interview collection began in October 2011 by a team of 25 interviewers and is ongoing.
Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).
Historical Note
Forty-five years ago, interracially married couples faced prosecution and jail time, or violence, if they happened to cross into one of sixteen states that prohibited and punished marriages on the basis of racial classifications. Sixty years ago, anti-miscegenation laws were on the books in thirty states. Eighty-two years ago, in 1930, the Hays Code forbade portrayals of interracial romance, curtailing the careers of actors of color like Anna May Wong who could no longer play romantic leads. In Germany in 1935, The Nuremberg Laws were introduced that prohibited marriage between Jewish Germans and other Germans. The only other nation to legislate against intermarriage was Apartheid South Africa in 1949. While interfaith marriages were not legally proscribed in the United States, interfaith and interclass marriages often met with opposition from family and community. And yet, in less than two generations since the last anti-miscegenation laws were removed, a study released by the Pew Research Center in 2010 reports that a record one out of seven new marriages in the United States were between spouses of a different race or ethnicity. The 2010 U.S. Census revealed that multiracial and multiethnic children are one of the country’s fastest-growing demographic groups.
The Crossing Borders, Bridging Generations Project aims to explore these historical ideas through modern day interviews with multiple generations of Brooklynites. It is an oral history project and public programming series which examines the history and experiences of mixed-heritage people and families, cultural hybridity, race, ethnicity, and identity in the historically diverse borough of Brooklyn. Through sharing stories, we open up intergenerational conversations about preserving cultural heritage in a multicultural democracy. Narrators came to this project through connections with the project the interviewing team and CBBG public programs.
Crossing Borders, Bridging Generations is a project of the Brooklyn Historical Society which builds upon BHS's oral history collections. Begun in 1973, the oral history collections contain interviews with more than 500 narrators and are available for listening in the Othmer Library. Crossing Borders, Bridging Generations is an ongoing project that is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities, the Institute for Museum and Library Services, and New York Council for the Humanities.
Conditions Governing Access
These oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives, and with you. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared.
Scope and Contents
The interviews in this collection are about mixed heritage identity and the borough of Brooklyn. For the purposes of this project, the definition of mixed was kept open and fluid, allowing narrators to have the space to describe themselves in their own words. Thought all interviewers took a life history approach to these interviews, they were collected by a team of over 25 interviewers and the content reflects different styles of interviewing and differing levels of famliarity between the interviewer and narrator.
Arrangement Note
This collection is arranged by each interviews accession number which was given at the time the interview came to the Brooklyn Historical Society.
Related Archival Materials Note
Please see the Crossing Borders, Bridging Generations website cbbg.brooklynhistory.org for related resources and project news.
Acculturation; Americanization; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Citizenship; Cultural assimilation; Ethnicity; Family life; Heritage; Identity politics; Interracial marriage; Mass media and ethnic relations; Minorities |z United States |x Social conditions; Miscegnation; Multiculturalism; New York (N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; New York (State) |x Ethnic relations; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; Race relations |z United States; Racially mixed people; Religion
- Shawn Elgart 2011.019.001, 1971-2011; 2011.019.001
  Historical Note
  Shawn Elgart is an African American woman who lives in Brooklyn with her husband and their daughter.
  Scope and Contents
  In this interview, Shawn Elgart discusses her interracial marriage and family.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This interview is only available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library. Please contact the library before your visit regarding access to this interview. For information about visiting the library, please see http://www.brooklynhistory.org/library/visit.html.
  California; Conversion |x Judaism; Interracial dating; Interracial marriage; Judaism; Motherhood; Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Religion
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Shawn Elgart, 1971-2011
    1 hour 30 minutes
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Shawn Elgart, 1971-2011
    36 pages
- Teresa Ish 2011.019.002, 1978-2011; 2011.019.002
  During this interview, Ish offers a detailed account of what it was like to be raised by an interracial couple and how her life has been influenced by her mixed-heritage. She talks about celebrating the Chinese New Year and her Grandmother’s hybrid Chinese-American versions of traditional Chinese dishes, such as peanut butter bao. In addition to her own memories, Ish recalled stories of her Grandmother and Great Grandmother in Malaysia. In the interview, she reflects on what it was like to physically appear culturally ambiguous and how, as an avid traveler, this has given her an advantage as she can blend in almost anywhere in the world. She elaborates on these types of positive aspects of having a mixed-heritage, but also voices frustrations about racial prejudices towards Chinese culture in America. Ish also speaks about the experience of raising her daughter in Brooklyn and contemplates what her life will be like and how she will be perceived.
  Teresa Ish grew up in Fresno, California and is of Chinese-Malaysian and Swedish descent. She attended UC Santa Cruz for both her undergraduate and graduate studies. Ish studied Marine Biology and co-founded FishWise, a nonprofit consultancy that promotes seafood sustainability. She met her husband in college and now lives in Brooklyn with her husband and daughter.
  Open to researchers without restriction.
  California; Chinese Americans; Food |x Social aspects; International cooking; Motherhood; Multiculturalism; Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Passing (Identity)
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Teresa Ish, 1978-2011
    2 hours 31 minutes
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Teresa Ish, 1978-2011
    72 pages
- Itamar Goldstein 2011.019.004, 1983-2011; 2011.019.004
  Itamar Goldstein is a 28-year-old medical student, born in Jeruslaem, Israel in 1983. His mother is a Yemenite Jew and his father is an American Jew. He came to the U.S. for undergrad at Columbia and moved to SUNY Downstate to study medicine.
  Goldstein talks about living with “roots across the ocean,” roots both in Israrel and in New York City. He talks about growing up in a mixed community, where everyone was a mix—part Moroccan and part American, etc. He talks about his first experiences in the U.S. at 10, after his parents divorced. He reflects on the differences between Judaism in Israel and in the U.S. He relates what a small and intimate community he grew up in, among Yemenite Jews, and the mix of Arab and Hebrew that he grew up speaking. He talks about how people never know what he is, whether he’s Mexican or Arab or Mediterranean. He talks about the way things like the Israeli army, travel, and the decision to be a doctor shaped him.
  Divorce; Ethnicity; Hebrew language; Israel; Judaism; Multiculturalism; Racially mixed people; Travel
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Itamar Goldstein, 1983-2011
    1 hour 59 minutes
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Itamar Goldstein, 1983-2011
    24 pages
- Madeleine Kanai 2011.019.005, 1979-2011; 2011.019.005
  Historical note
  Madeleine Kanai grew up in Kobe, Japan and Lexington, Kentucky. Her father is also of mixed heritage (Japanese and American) and her mother is from Kentucky. Kanai lived in Brooklyn, New York for a period of time before moving into Manhattan.
  In her interview, Kanai explores her Japanese heritage. She speaks Japanese as her first language but remembers being treated poorly when she lived in Japan. In one instance, she visited Hiroshima with her mother and overheard people talking about them in Japanese. She moved to Lexington, Kentucky when she was eight years old. Kanai has a very strong connection to her own family history and is able to trace her family back through many generations.
  Asian Americans; Ethnicity; Families; Language and languages; Motherhood
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Madeleine Kanai, 1979-2011
    1 hour 13 minutes
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Madeleine Kanai, 1979-2011
    27 pages
- Harry Schwartzman 2011.019.006, 1976-2011; 2011.019.006
  Harry Schwartzman’s mother is Japanese and his father is Jewish. He grew up speaking Japanese, Yiddish and English. Schwartzman is from New York and has traveled and lived in many other places. He currently calls Brooklyn home.
  In his interview, Schwartzman talks about growing up speaking Japanese and Yiddish. He did not start speaking English until he attended nursery school. He has a deep connection to New York, and noticed differences between the way people reacted to him and his brother on their frequent visits to Japan.
  Japanese Americans; Japanese language; Judaism; Language and languages; Travel; Yiddish language
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Harry Schwartzman, 1976-2011
    1 hour 1 minute
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Harry Schwartzman, 1976-2011
    21 pages
- Daniela Caraballo 2011.019.007, 1987-2011; 2011.019.007
  In this interview, Caraballo discusses her Dominican and Puerto Rican heritage, her upbringing and education, and her decision to become a social worker.
  Daniela Caraballo grew up in Sunset Park and Bensonhurst and is of Dominican and Puerto Rican descent. She currently lives in Brooklyn and is a social worker.
  Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Divorce; Dominican Americans; Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.)
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Daniela Caraballo, 1987-2011
    1 hour 22 minutes
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Daniela Caraballo, 1987-2011
    32 pages
- Lisa Heller 2011.019.008, 1967-2011; 2011.019.008
  Lisa Hiller identifies as biracial (black and white) and grew up in the Bronx in a Jewish family. She currently lives in Brooklyn.
  In this interview, Heller discusses her upbringing in New York City and how her understanding of her biracial identity changed over time.
  Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Community activists; Judaism; Motherhood; Racially mixed people
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Lisa Heller, 1967-2011
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Lisa Heller, 1967-2011
    30 pages
- Katherine Ambia 2011.019.009, 1983-2012; 2011.019.009
  Katherine Ambia grew up in Sunset Park, Brooklyn with her twin brother, her White-American mother and Peruvian father. She got her bachelor’s in Latin American studies from Wesleyan, her MSW from Columbia University, and is currently training as a clinician with the Yale Child Study Center's Intensive In-home Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Services program.
  In this interview, Ambia discusses the way her racial identity has changed over time, from growing up in the culturally and economically mixed neighborhood of Sunset Park and attending a Quaker elementary school in Brooklyn Heights, to studying critical race theory formally as a young adult at Wesleyan University. Ambia elaborates on the cultural and economic backgrounds of her parents, who met as community organizers in the 1970s. She tells the story of her father’s childhood in a small indigenous village in Peru, his coming to the U.S., and his first experiences with American racism. She also tells the stories of her mother and maternal grandmother, an enterprising groundbreaker who worked in advertising in New York in the fifties, when the field was dominated by men.
  She describes her parents as political organizers with a passion for worker and immigrant rights. Ambia remembers going to protests and growing up with those same values as a child. She also vividly accounts her personal experience of being mixed race, touching on the silence around the issue in her household, her trips to Peru to visit her father’s family, the messages she received from her maternal grandmother, as well as the racism she encountered in school from peers. As an adult, she reconciles her experience growing up mixed-race; how what she studied and whom she met in college has helped her develop a language around talking about her identity that she didn’t have as a child.
  American Dream; Boerum Hill (New York, N.Y.); Group identity; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Human skin color; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; Racism |z New York (State) |z New York; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); WASPs (Persons); White privilege
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Katherine Ambia, 1983-2012
    1 hour
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Katherine Ambia, 1983-2012
    25 pages
- Asha Sundararaman 2011.019.010, 1982-2012; 2011.019.010
  Sundararaman is a woman of Indian and white heritage who identifies as a third culture kid. Originally from California, she has lived in many other places including India, Indiana, London and Brooklyn. She currently works in an administrative capacity at a non-profit that provides international blindness prevention healthcare.
  In her interivew, Sundararaman talks about her experiences being multiracial in difference places across the country and around the world. She felt the most at home in Angola, where she felt difference was understood and accepted and not scrutinized like in California or in Indiana. Diversity has been important in her friend groups and in her interview she discusses how race has played out in groups where she was the one or one of two people of color. She also talks about her parents’ relationship with each other and with their in-laws.
  Families; Multiculturalism; Travel
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Asha Sundaraman, 1982-2012
    1 hour 41 minutes
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Asha Sundararaman, 1982-2012
- Alexander David 2011.019.011, 1993-2012; 2011.019.012
  David is a sophomore at City College, enrolled as a Macaulay Honors student and majoring in biomedical engineering. He attended Stuyvesant High School where he played baseball and football. He identifies as mixed-heritage because his mother is of Chinese descent and his father is of Romanian descent.
  During his interview, David discusses his many identities: mixed-heritage, a student, and an athlete. He describes his transition from Middle School to High School and the social and academic adjustments that they demanded of him. David’s mixed heritage identity has impacted him throughout his upbringing in Brooklyn and life as a student. He tells the story of how his parents became acquainted and discusses the effect of cultural-mixing on his self-perception and reception of others. He describes his motivations for founding a club for mixed-heritage students at Stuyvesant High School and enumerates the discussions that the students partook in during meetings, including how mothers would often mix dishes from two cultures to create their own hybrid recipes. He also talks about how his mixed identity plays out in other areas of his life. For example, unlike most pitchers in baseball, he also hits and does not play the field.
  College students |z New York (State) |z New York; Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Multiculturalism; Sports |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Student life and customs |z New York (State) |z New York
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Alexander David, 2012 January 13
    1 hour 8 minutes
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Alexander David, 2012 January 13
    42 pages
- Julie Kline 2011.019.012, 1980-2012; 2011.019.012
  Julie Kline is from Oakland California and grew up in a multi-faith family. She currently lives in Brooklyn.
  In this interview, Kline talks about her family and ancestry, growing up in California, and the many transitional periods in her life, including her move to Brooklyn.
  Artists |z New York (State) |z New York; California; Interfaith families; Interfaith marriage; Judaism; Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Religion; Theater |z New York (State) |z New York
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Julie Kline, 1980-2012
    1 hour 51 minutes
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Julie Kline, 1980-2012
    48 pages
- Katherine Ambia 2011.019.013, 1983-2012
  In Ambia’s second interview, she goes into more into detail about her childhood experiences. She talks about feeling isolated or bullied at times during her childhood, while also feeling a close connection to her friends on her block and at her Quaker school. She describes her experience of female friendship as a kid; including where and when race came into that dynamic. She shows us the inside of her childhood home: filled with elaborate games, toys, art projects, Disney movies, story writing, no television and a lot of health food. Ambia also talks about her interest in sports, cooking, and holistic health helped her connect with her father.
  Ambia talks about the differing ideas of race within her own family and how her brother’s experience around these issues differs from her own. She also relates how her family would celebrate holidays with the two separate sides of her multiracial family, and she tells stories about the differing rituals. She goes on to talk about her parents’ separation in high school and what she has learned about relationships from watching her own family. She describes her own experiences of dating and her racial identity.
  Ambia also focuses a lot on the effect her education has had on who she is today. She talks about teachers who’ve profoundly affected her both before and in college, exciting her interest in literature, race in society, social justice and her own cultural background. She tells us is in detail about her formative year abroad in Bolivia and more generally, about her broad and rich education at Wesleyan and the acceptance she found there. At the end of the interview, she talks about her choices around her profession. Ambia talks about how her commitment to social justice and equality contributed to her decision to become a therapist. She discusses some possible long-term goals such as building a psychiatric practice and expresses her enthusiasm for the CBBG project and the importance of this kind of work.
  Childhood; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Female friendship; Friendship; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Peruvian American; Social service
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Katherine Ambia, 1983-2012
    1 hour 35 minutes
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Katherine Ambia, 1983-2012
    26 pages
- Lenge Hong 2011.019.014, 1966-2012; 2011.019.014
  Lenge Hong is of Chinese and Scottish heritage and originally from Miami, Florida. She lived in the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn while attending NYU. Lenge currently lives in Manhattan and works as a library cataloger with a collection of historic photographs.
  In this interview, Hong talks about her experiences being multiracial at a time and in a place where it was largely misunderstood. She grew up in Miami, Florida where her father owned and operated a Chinese restaurant, of which she holds fond memories. Most people in Miami assumed she was Cuban or Native American. Most people did not think Hong was Asian and most of the Asians in the area were a part of her family. She also talks about having visited Hawaii which was one of the only times she has felt like she has totally blended in. She spends time reflecting on the difference in attitude and acceptance toward multiracial people in the 1970s and the present. Hong wonders how her life would have been different if she hadn't grown up with a Chinese name, which both her and her sister were given. She also talks about her experience answering the question "what are you?" which she got asked many times growing up. Her feelings and answers to this question have changed over her lifetime.
  Chinese Americans; Family life; Florida; Multiculturalism; Names
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Lenge Hong, 1966-2012
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Lenge Hong, 1966-2012
- Sonnet Takahisa 2011.019.015, 1956-2012; 2011.019.015
  Raised in Brooklyn by a Japanese father and a Jewish mother of Russian/Polish heritage, Sonnet Takahisa transforms her past and current multi-cultural family background into unique professional expertise that she applies in museums, art and cultural institutions and schools.
  In her interview, Sonnet describes the Japanese family traditions of her father and the family traditions of her Jewish mother. She spends time reflecting on the experiences of different generations of her family with respect to ethnicity and identity perception. She talks about her upbringing in Brooklyn, especially her experiences with grade school, with college, and with her first jobs.
  Acculturation; Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Ethnicity; Families; Museums
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Sonnet Takahisa, 2012 January 31
    1 hour 55 minutes
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Sonnet Takahisa, 2012 January 31
    41 pages
- Alicia Piller 2011.019.016, 1982-2012; 2011.019.016
  Alicia Piller is an artist and jewelry designer living in Brooklyn, New York. Originally from Chicago, Illinois, her mother is African American and her father is Jewish and of Belgian and Polish descent.
  In this interview, Piller discusses her upbringing in Chicago, her ancestry and multifaith family, her college experience, and her work as in artist in Brooklyn. She identifies as culturally Jewish.
  Artists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Chicago (Ill.); Christianity; Interfaith families; Interfaith marriage; Interracial marriage; Judaism; Racially mixed people
  - Oral History Interview (audio) with Alicia Piller, 1982-2012
  - Oral History Interview (transcript) with Alicia Piller, 1982-2012
    64 pages
- Vilray Bolles 2011.019.017, 1985-2012; 2011.019.017
  Vilray Bolles grew up in Park Slope, Brooklyn. His father is American and his mother is from Nicaragua. Bolles currently works as a musician.